<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geodesic on Yan Zhang</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/geodesic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geodesic on Yan Zhang</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 15:18:52 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/geodesic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Geodesics via the Calculus of Variations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/geodesics-via-calculus-of-variation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/geodesics-via-calculus-of-variation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I explain geodesics to people, I usually use two intuitions:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Geodesics are the &amp;ldquo;straight lines&amp;rdquo; on curved surfaces, and;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Geodesics minimize distances between two points on curved surfaces.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;definition&lt;/strong&gt; I used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://yaz62.github.io/posts/prove-meridians-are-geodesics/&#34;  class=&#34;external-link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; is basically a more precise version of the first intuition, using the tool of parallel transport to define what is considered &amp;ldquo;straight&amp;rdquo; on a curved surface. However, for people who study Lagrangian mechanics, a definition based on the second intuition might be more straightforward, as the geodesic is the path that minimizes the action, if we define the action as the Euclidean distance between points.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prove That Meridians Are Geodesics With LLMs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/prove-meridians-are-geodesics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/prove-meridians-are-geodesics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I tried to prove that meridians on a surface of revolution are always geodesics, but my calculations suggested otherwise unless a certain condition was met.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I consulted ChatGPT and Claude; both initially gave confusing or circular reasoning, but Claude provided a clue that led me to the answer.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The key insight: the geodesic equation requires the curve to be parametrized with constant speed (affine parametrization).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Parallel transport preserves the length of the tangent vector, so the tangent must have constant speed along a geodesic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The collaborative exploration with LLMs brought more satisfaction than just getting the answer directly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learned bits of differential geometry over the years, and I always use Theodore Shifrin&amp;rsquo;s notes, &lt;em&gt;Differential Geometry: A First Course in Curves and Surfaces&lt;/em&gt;, as my textbook. Recently, I decided to pick it back up just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
